Guide to the Harriet R. Holman Papers, 1869-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Harriet R. Holman papers 1869-1986
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Holman, Harriet R. (Harriet Rebecca), 1912-1992.
16.5 Linear Feet About 7899 Items
Author and professor of English from Anderson, S.C.
Collection is chiefly significant for Holman's correspondence with writers, publishers and colleagues concerning the teaching and writing of American literature. Significant correspondents include Jay B. Hubbell, Rayburn Moore, Henry Field, Ann Page Johns, Armistead C. Gordon, Jr., Dr. Jeremiah N. Fusco, Corydon Bell, Guy Davenport, Edith Buchanan, Margaret Meaders, David Stocking, Marion Kingston Stocking, Newman I. White, E. M. Lander, Jr., Mattie U. Russell, and members of the Thomas Nelson Page and John Fox families. There are also letters from South Carolina authors, including Rosa Pendleton Chiles, Sidelle Ellis, Patricia Kneas Hill, Katharine M. Jones, Mary Boone Robertson Longley, and Alice L. O’Connell. Also includes works written or edited by Holman and others, a typed transcription of Cherokee stories as told by Mary Ulmer Chiltoskey, clippings, notecard files, printed material, and photographs of Thomas Nelson and Florence Lathrop Page, and Nannie Mae Tilley.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Some portions are unprocessed.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Harriet R. Holman Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1969, 1987, and 2008.
Collection Overview
The papers of Harriet Rebecca Holman span the years 1869-1986, and are chiefly significant for Holman's correspondence with writers, publishers and colleagues concerning the teaching and writing of American literature. Significant correspondents include Jay B. Hubbell, Rayburn Moore, Henry Field, Ann Page Johns, Armistead C. Gordon, Jr., Dr. Jeremiah N. Fusco, Corydon Bell, Guy Davenport, Edith Buchanan, Margaret Meaders, David Stocking, Marion Kingston Stocking, Newman I. White, E. M. Lander, Jr., Mattie U. Russell and members of the Thomas Nelson Page and John Fox families. The Page family materials constitute a large portion of the materials in this collection and are represented by their own series. There are also letters from South Carolina authors, including Rosa Pendleton Chiles, Sidelle Ellis, Patricia Kneas Hill, Katharine M. Jones, Mary Boone Robertson Longley, and Alice L. O’Connell. Also includes works written or edited by Holman and others, a typed transcription of Cherokee stories as told by Mary Ulmer Chiltoskey, clippings, notecard files, printed material, and photographs of Thomas Nelson and Florence Lathrop Page, and Nannie Mae Tilley. Acquired as part of the Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography at Duke University.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
American literature -- History and criticism
American literature -- Study and teaching
Authors, American -- South Carolina
Authors, American -- Southern states
Bell, Corydon, 1894-
Buchanan, Edith
Cherokee Indians -- Folklore
Chiltoskey, Mary Ulmer
Chiles, Rosa Pendleton, b. 1866
College teachers -- Correspondence
Davenport, Guy
Ellis, Sidelle B., 1906-
Field, Henry
Fox, John, Jr
Fusco, Jeremiah N.
Gordon, Armistead C., Jr
Hill, Patricia Kneas
Holman, Harriet R. (Harriet Rebecca), 1912-
Hubbell, Jay B. (Jay Broadus), 1885-1979
Johns, Ann Page
Jones, Katharine M. (Katharine Macbeth), 1900-
Lander, E. M., Jr
Longley, Mary Boone Robertson
Meaders, Margaret
Moore, Rayburn S., 1920-
O’Connell, Alice L. (Alice Louise), 1907-
Page, Thomas Nelson, 1853-1922
Page, Florence Lathrop, 1858-1921
Photographs.
Russell, Mattie U.
Stocking, David
Stocking, Marion Kingston
Tilley, Nannie M. (Nannie May), 1898-
White, Newman Ivey, 1892-1948
Duke University. Jay B. Hubbell Center for American Literary Historiography
Related Material
Thoman Nelson Page Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Jay B. Hubbell Papers
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Contents of Collection
- General Files Series, 1947-1971, (8 boxes)
  - Correspondence (Box 1-2)
  - Writings: Harriet R. Holman (Box 3)
  - Writings (Box 4)
  - Miscellany (Box 5)
  - Volumes (Box 6)
  - Printed Material (Box 7-8)
- Thomas Nelson Page Series, 1869-1920, (16 boxes)
  - Correspondence, 1869-1892 (Box 9)
  - Correspondence, 1893-1900 (Box 10)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1905 (Box 11)
  - Correspondence, 1906-1908 (Box 12)
  - Correspondence, 1909-1912 (Box 13)
  - Correspondence, 1913 (Box 14)
  - Correspondence (Box 15)
  - Correspondence, 1918-1919 (Box 16)
  - Correspondence, 1920 (Box 17)
  - Correspondence (Box 18)
  - Embassy correspondence (Box 19)
  - Correspondence (Box 20)
  - Diary (Box 21-22)
  - Miscellany (Box 23)
  - Writings, 1869-1903 (Box 24)
- Other Authors Series, (3 boxes)
  - Henry Field (Box 25)
  - John Fox, Jr. (Box 26)
  - James Whitcomb Riley (Box 27)
- Card Files Series, (2 boxes)
  - Research notecard files (Box 28-29)
- Accession (1987), 1967-1978, 1988, (1 box)
  Contains a draft of Cherokee Stories told by the Cherokee Storytelling Lady of the Qualla Indian Boundary by Harriet Holman as well as correspondence relating to this work. Also contains correspondence with Rayburn Moore and his curriculum vitae.
  - Accession (1987) (Box 30)
- Original Accession, 1936-1983, (2 boxes)
  - Correspondence (Box 1)
  - Endowed professorship
  - Miscellaneous
  - Pictures (photographs) and clippings
  - South Carolina Poets
  - Turkish University program
  - Winthrop College
  - Writings
    - Printed Material
    - Reprints
  - Volumes (Box 2)